Danaja Maldeniya

University of Michigan

3340 North Quad

Email: dmal@umich.edu

Website: dmaldeniya.com

105 S. State St. Ann Arbor, MI 48108 Mobile: (734)-926-6380

RESEARCH INTERESTS My research interests are primarily in two broad domains; large-scale collaboration dynamics and city science. I'm interested in the mechanisms that drive diffusion of information and behaviors in social production settings as well as the interactions between different social, physical, transport and economic networks within cities.

EDUCATION PhD in Information Science

2016 - TBD

2011

University of MichiganAdvisor: Daniel Romero

BSc. in Computer Science & Engineering (First Class) University of Moratuwa, Sri Lanka

EMPLOYMENT

Research Assistant
University of Michigan, School of Information

Sep 2018 Ann Arbor, MI

Research Assistant

Jan 2018 - Apr 2018

University of Michigan, School of Information

Ann Arbor, MI

Graduate Student Instructor

University of Michigan, School of Information

Sep 2017 Dec 2017

Ann Arbor, MI

SI 301 - Models of Social Information Processing

Research Intern

Bell Laboratories, Social Dynamics Team

Jun 2017 - Aug 2017

Cambridge, UK

Research Assistant Sep 2016 - May 2017 University of Michigan, School of Information Ann Arbor, MI

Research Fellow Aug 2016 - present LIRNEasia Colombo, Sri Lanka

Senior Researcher Apr 2015 - Aug 2016
LIRNEasia, Big Data for Development Team Colombo, Sri Lanka

Researcher Apr 2014 - March 2015 LIRNEasia, Big Data for Development Team Colombo, Sri Lanka

Senior Software Engineer

Jan 2014 - Apr 2015

CodeGen International

Colombo, Sri Lanka

Software EngineerDec 2011 - Dec 2013CodeGen InternationalColombo, Sri Lanka

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

D. Maldeniya, C. Budak, L.P. Robert R, D.M. Romero. "Herding a Deluge of Good Samaritans: How GitHub Projects Respond to Increased Attention". Forthcoming

- J.E. Blumenstock, **D. Maldeniya**, and S. Lokanathan. "Understanding the Impact of Urban Infrastructure:New Insights from Population-Scale Data". The 9th IEEE/ACM International Conference on Information and Communication Technologies and Development (ICTD), 2017
- **D. Maldeniya**, A. Varghese, T. Stuart, and D.M. Romero. "The Role of Optimal Distinctiveness and Homophily in Online Dating." Proc. 11th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM), 2017
- R. Samarajiva, S. Lokanathan, K. Madhawa, G. Kriendler, **D. Maldeniya**, "Big data to improve urban planning", Economic and Political Weekly, Vol. L, No. 22, 2015.

OTHER PUBLICATIONS

- **D.** Maldeniya, A. Kumarage, S. Lokanathan, G. Kriendler, K. Madhawa, "Where did you come from? Where did you go? Robust policy relevant evidence from mobile network big data", CPRSouth, 2015.
- K. Madhawa, S. Lokanathan, **D. Maldeniya**, R. Samarajiva, "Using mobile network data for land use classification", CPRSouth, 2015.
- K. Madhawa, S. Lokanathan, R. Samarajiva, **D. Maldeniya**, "Understanding communities using mobile network big data", CPRSouth, 2015.
- **D.** Maldeniya, S. Lokanathan, A. Kumarage, "Origin-Destination matrix estimation for Sri Lanka using mobile network big data", 13th International Conference on Social Implications of Computers in Developing Countries, 2015.
- K. Madhawa, S. Lokanathan, **D. Maldeniya**, R. Samarajiva, "Land use classification using call detail records" (Poster Abstract), NetMob, 2015.
- N. de Silva, A. Perera, **D. Maldeniya**, "Semi-supervised Algorithm for Concept Ontology Based Word Set Expansion", International Conference on Advances in ICT for Emerging Regions(ICTER), 2013.

SCHOLARLY PRESENTATIONS

- "Psychological Response of Communities affected by Natural Disasters in Social Media", UMTweetCon2019
- "Psychological Response of Communities affected by Natural Disasters in Social Media", MIDAS Symposium 2018 (Award for Most Innovative Use of Data)

Professional Service

- Reviewing: EPJ Data Science, ICWSM 2020, WWW 2020, WSDM 2020, ICDM 2020, Nature Scientific Reports, WWW 2018, WSDM 2018
- Mentoring: Kaifeng Chen (Masters Student), Stella Choi (Masters Student), Jiaxin Ye (Undegraduate Student), Eric Lian (Undergraduate Student)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Graduate Student Instructor University of Michigan, School of Information

Sep 2017 Dec 2017 Ann Arbor, MI

• SI 301 - Models of Social Information Processing